<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fortunes fashion pourtrayed in the troubles of the Ladie Elizabeth Gray, wife to Edward the fourth. Written by Tho. Sampson.</title>
            <author>Sampson, Thomas, poet.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11433</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21686</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104563</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840296</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840296</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4783</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11433)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4783)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 858:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fortunes fashion pourtrayed in the troubles of the Ladie Elizabeth Gray, wife to Edward the fourth. Written by Tho. Sampson.</title>
                  <author>Sampson, Thomas, poet.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Field] for William Iones, and are to be sold at his shop at White-crosse streete end by the church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The troubles of the Lady Elizabeth Gray.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elizabeth, --  Consort of Edward IV, King of England, 1437?-1492 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4783:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4783:1"/>
            <p>FORTVNES FASHION, Pourtrayed in the troubles of the <hi>Ladie Elizabeth Gray, wife to</hi> EDWARD the fourth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by</hi> Tho. Sampſon.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Richard Field</figDesc>
               <head>ANCHORA SPEI</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Iones,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at White-croſſe ſtreete end by the Church. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4783:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4783:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS MANY WAIES INDEERED FRIEND M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Henry Pilkington of Gadsby, in the Countie of Leiceſter, Gentleman.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, this Tragicall hiſtory being no fiction, but a true relation of the many troubles of a diſtreſſed Queene, I offer to your patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage for two eſpeciall cauſes; the one, for the long continued loue betweene vs; the other, for that I know your name is a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent protection for it and me, againſt the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny find-faults that this age is peſtered with, who themſelues being not able, or too idle to do any thing worth the reading, yet are compoſed of ſuch a ſnarling ſubſtance, that nothing can eſcape their eye or eare with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſcoffe: how euer it diſpleaſeth ſuch, I care not; if it content you, I haue my deſire,
<pb facs="tcp:4783:3"/>
not doubting but when you are wearied with more ſerious ſtudies, you will at ſome times peruſe this. And ſo I leaue you to liue happily.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your aſſured friend <hi>THO. SAMPSON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:4783:3"/>
            <head>The Argument for the better vnderſtanding of the Readers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen Henry the ſixt king of that name in England, was by the Earle of Warwicke, and others, thought vnmeete to gouerne the kingdome: and Edward the fourth claimed the Crowne, in a battell neare to Saint Albans: Henry the ſixt was taken priſoner in the <hi>39</hi> yeare of his reigne, Anno Dom. <hi>1461.</hi> All king Henries forces were ſlaine, or put to flight, amongst whom was ſlain on king Henries part, one Sir Iohn Gray, husband of this Lady Elizabeth Gray, of whoſe troubles this hiſtorie now diſcourſeth. This Lady was after maried to king Edward the fourth: ſhe was daughter to the Lady Iaquet, daughter to Peter Earle of Saint Paul, neece to the Lord Lewis of Leutzenbrugh, which Lady Iaquet was firſt married to Iohn Duke of Bedford and Regent of France; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhe was married to Sir Richard Woodvile Lord Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, by whom ſhe had this Lady Elizabeth and others. When king Edward was ſetled in his kingdome, and had impriſoned Henry the ſixt in the Tower of London: the Earle of Warwicke was ſent into France, to intreate a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage betweene King Edward the fourth and the Lady Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, daughter to Lewis Duke of Sauoy, and ſister to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Carlot then wife to the French King, in whoſe Court this Lady Bona then was: which motion was well liked of by the French King, and all things ſorted to the Earle of Warwicks deſire. But in the meane time, while theſe things were working in France, King Edward going to his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Grafton, in the countie of Northampton; in the time
<pb facs="tcp:4783:4"/>
of the Kings remaining there, this Lady Gray was an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſuter to the King, that ſhe might haue her Ioynter gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen her; which becauſe her husband was ſlaine on King Henries part, was ſince his death detained from her. King Edward liked her ſo well, that after many amorous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes ſhe was married to him at Grafton, where firſt he fancied her. The Kings mother and many of the Nobilitie did diſlike of this mariage, becauſe ſhe was a widow, and his ſubiect. This King was married to this Lady Gray, before the Earle of Warwicke was returned from France, which ſome ſay, who will talke much and know little, was the cauſe of the warres afterwards betweene the King and the Earle. But the Earles hatred againſt the King was for another cauſe, as in the Chronicles you may reade. What troubles and griefe happened to this Queene in the time of her husband the Kings life, and after his death, you may imagine. You ſee her newly riſen out of her graue, and in the extremity of her griefe ſpeaking as followeth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4783:4"/>
            <head>The troubles of the Ladie <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Gray wife to Edward the fourth.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>SOmetime I was, vnhappie was that time,</l>
               <l>Wherein I liu'd, and neuer taſted ioyes,</l>
               <l>That did not wither, ere they were in prime:</l>
               <l>Honors are ſuch vncertaine fading toyes.</l>
               <l>I was king Edwards wife, a wofull Queene,</l>
               <l>As in this hiſtory may plaine be ſeene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O had my loue in my firſt choice remaind,</l>
               <l>How happie had I bene, from griefe how free?</l>
               <l>Of wofull haps I neuer had complaind,</l>
               <l>But that muſt needs be, that the fates decree.</l>
               <l>The Cottage ſeated in the dale below,</l>
               <l>Stands ſafe, when higheſt towers do ouerthrow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My youth was bleſt in loue with equall choice,</l>
               <l>The matter fit prepared for loues fier:</l>
               <l>In which while I conſum'd, nere did my voice,</l>
               <l>Nor thoughts conſent, to wiſh my fortunes higher.</l>
               <l>Thus in the valley, whil'ſt my loue did reſt,</l>
               <l>My loue though lowly, none more highly bleſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But fatall powers, with vnreuerſd decree,</l>
               <l>Whom hecatombs of prayers may not perſwade,</l>
               <l>To adde one minute to the bliſſe they ſee,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:5"/>Or ſpare one day, what but a day was made:</l>
               <l>Their courſe is fixt, and cannot be preuented,</l>
               <l>They beſt abide their might, that are contented.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe power in me diſtreſſed erſt was knowne,</l>
               <l>When Edward fourth of name, obtaind the Crowne,</l>
               <l>And put ſixt Henry from his regall throne,</l>
               <l>Raiſing himſelfe by caſting others downe.</l>
               <l>Greedy Ambition, endleſſe in deſiring,</l>
               <l>On others ruine foundeth her aſpiring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There firſt began the groundworke of my woe,</l>
               <l>There loſt I him that had my prime of loue:</l>
               <l>And then the prime of ſorrowes I did know,</l>
               <l>In prime of ioy, which did more ſorrowes moue.</l>
               <l>The daintieſt palate, with exacteſt skill,</l>
               <l>Diſtaſts the reliſh of the bitter pill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There was my husband ſlaine on Henries part,</l>
               <l>Then was I left a widow deſolate:</l>
               <l>Yet once againe, loue choſe another dart,</l>
               <l>Whoſe golden head I thought would raiſe my fate;</l>
               <l>King Edwards loue I meane; but what enſude?</l>
               <l>The Crowne I gain'd, I euer after rewde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To Witchwood forreſt when this King did go,</l>
               <l>For his delight to hunt the fearfull Deere:</l>
               <l>He went to Grafton; thence my ſecond woe</l>
               <l>Did ſpring, it was my hap then to be there,</l>
               <l>Attendant on my mother, in which ſpace,</l>
               <l>I was an humble Suter to his Grace,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:5"/>
               <l>That he would pleaſe to pitie my eſtate,</l>
               <l>That I might haue my Ioynter giuen me:</l>
               <l>Seeing my hopes were then ſo ruinate,</l>
               <l>That I was like to taſte of miſerie.</l>
               <l>Such was my caſe, except it were relieued:</l>
               <l>At my complaint, he very much was grieued.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And mou'd with pitie, did commiſerate</l>
               <l>My cauſe, my ſelfe he ſeem'd to fancie then:</l>
               <l>With gracious words lamenting my eſtate,</l>
               <l>Bad me take comfort; ô the wiles of men!</l>
               <l>He courted me, and I at laſt did yeeld,</l>
               <l>My honor ſau'd, that he ſhould win the field.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A King to woo his ſubiect in ſuch ſort,</l>
               <l>As no diſhonor by his loue might riſe:</l>
               <l>Blame me not then, if to that princely port,</l>
               <l>I was contented to be led as prize:</l>
               <l>Where honor grac'd with regall maieſtie,</l>
               <l>Was Pilot to my ſhip in ieopardie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though long he ſude, I granted at the laſt</l>
               <l>To be his wife, ſuch ſhew of honeſt loue</l>
               <l>His princely heart did ſeeme to haue embrac'd:</l>
               <l>I was content the nuptiall ſports to proue.</l>
               <l>No wanton luſt did harbour in my thought,</l>
               <l>Although too deare I haue my pleaſure bought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When it was bruted, that the King affected,</l>
               <l>And would without the liking of his Lords</l>
               <l>Eſpouſe me; ſeeing that he not reſpected</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:6"/>Their diſcontent, nor ſmooth intreating words:</l>
               <l>But like a loyall and a royall King,</l>
               <l>Would ſtill make good his vowes in euery thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then they deuiſde againſt me to obiect,</l>
               <l>My widowhood, ô that was chiefly it,</l>
               <l>Wherewith they thought me fouly to detect,</l>
               <l>Alledging it was rare, and farre vnfit,</l>
               <l>A King ſhould fancie ſuch a one as I,</l>
               <l>That was a widow, and in pouertie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But all in vaine they ſought him to diſſwade,</l>
               <l>He gaue his word, and conſtantly did ſtand,</l>
               <l>Vnto the oathes betwixt vs firmly made,</l>
               <l>With interchange of hearts, and gift of hand.</l>
               <l>He did deſire our marriage day to ſee,</l>
               <l>And I did wiſh that time as much as he.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When the Kings mother thought it was in vaine,</l>
               <l>To vſe perſwaſions to her ſonne the King:</l>
               <l>A precontract ſhe ſpared not to faine,</l>
               <l>That he had made, his honor ſo to bring</l>
               <l>Into reproch; ſuppoſing that the way,</l>
               <l>From marriage a while to cauſe him ſtay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But then the King thoſe cauils did diſproue,</l>
               <l>And we at Grafton married were with ſpeed:</l>
               <l>And there with holy rites did ſeale our loue,</l>
               <l>Which God and man allow as ſacred deed.</l>
               <l>There were we ioyn'd in holy mariage ſtate,</l>
               <l>Which during life ſhould be inuiolate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:6"/>
               <l>Whether the King did keepe his plighted faith</l>
               <l>To me, as marriage ſtrictly doth require:</l>
               <l>Or if it be that he it broken hath,</l>
               <l>Which I to know, or proue, do not deſire:</l>
               <l>I liu'd and lou'd him in ſuch duteous ſort,</l>
               <l>As let my life and actions make report.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Before the Earle made his returne from France,<note place="margin">Richard Neuil then Earle of Warwicke.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Being ſent to treate a mariage for the King</l>
               <l>With Lady Bona, time brought forth this chance,</l>
               <l>The King was married, which ſome ſay did bring</l>
               <l>The fall and ruine of King Edwards ſeed,</l>
               <l>(The vulgar peoples ſaying is no creed.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How dares a ſubiect contradict his King?</l>
               <l>Muſt ſubiects wils limit their Princes loue?</l>
               <l>It's more then vaine, yea a preſumptuous thing,</l>
               <l>Inferiors ſhould ſuch bold commanders proue,</l>
               <l>To tie Kings thoughts to fancie none but them</l>
               <l>That pleaſe their ſubiects, ô aſpiring men!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What though things ſorted to the Earles deſire?</l>
               <l>And Lewis Duke of Sauoy was content,</l>
               <l>To grant as much as Warwicke did require:</l>
               <l>Muſt princely Edward ſuffer baniſhment?</l>
               <l>Or be obedient to his ſubiects frowne,</l>
               <l>Or hazard all the glorie of a Crowne?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It was not this that cauſd the Earle rebell,</l>
               <l>Nor was it conſcience of King Henries right:</l>
               <l>Another cauſe, ſome hiſtories do tell,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:7"/>Enraged Warwicke, and did cauſe him fight</l>
               <l>Againſt his King; yet Kings can giue no cauſe,</l>
               <l>Sufficient motiues for the breach of lawes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O neuer let ſucceeding ages heare</l>
               <l>Vnto the ſtaine of his nobilitie,</l>
               <l>The wauering faith that Warwicke then did beare,</l>
               <l>Conſtant in nothing, but vnconſtancie:</l>
               <l>Firſt fauouring one, then changed to the other,</l>
               <l>Faithfull to none, although he were his brother.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet will I giue him, being dead, his due,</l>
               <l>For ſure it is a ſinne to wrong the dead,</l>
               <l>Though to his King he was vnkind, vntrue,</l>
               <l>His valour was by vanitie miſled:</l>
               <l>Who ſo him pleaſd, to raiſe vnto the Crowne;</l>
               <l>And when he liſt, by force to caſt them downe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A valiant Knight, and fortunate in warre,</l>
               <l>Vlyſſes-like for prudent policie:</l>
               <l>Yet this did all his other vertues marre,</l>
               <l>And was a blot to his poſteritie,</l>
               <l>That right or wrong he car'd not how it was,</l>
               <l>But as he would, ſo things ſhould come to paſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O no, another fire the world doth know,</l>
               <l>Betwixt the King and Warwicke kindled was:</l>
               <l>Which I by no meanes to the world will ſhow,</l>
               <l>It was too much (if ſo it was) alas,</l>
               <l>That ſuch a blot ſhould blemiſh ſuch a King,</l>
               <l>That was ſo royall elſe in euery thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:7"/>
               <l>Ile nere beleeue that euer Edwards mind,</l>
               <l>Would paſſe the limits of true honors name:</l>
               <l>Although in hiſtories you there may find,</l>
               <l>Some things ſet downe that might empaire his fame:</l>
               <l>I was his wife, he lou'd me as I thought;</l>
               <l>I paid his loue with dutie, as I ought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The next yeare after that we married were,</l>
               <l>At Weſtminſter I then was crowned Queene:</l>
               <l>Attended there by many a noble Peere,</l>
               <l>In ſuch rare ſort as at ſuch times are ſeene.</l>
               <l>My father and my friends he did aduance,</l>
               <l>To greater place, but more vnhappie chance.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And in this yeare, into the world I brought</l>
               <l>A daughter, which combin'd King Edwards loue</l>
               <l>In double knot with mine: for ſure tis thought</l>
               <l>The pleaſingſt ioy that man and wife do proue,</l>
               <l>When of their honeſt loues, ſuch fruite they ſee,</l>
               <l>As farre beyond all other treaſures be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But oh, what pleaſure euer laſteth long?</l>
               <l>Some enuious fate maligning that our bliſſe</l>
               <l>Should long continue, with iniurious wrong</l>
               <l>Did ouerthrow our mirth, and forc'd vs miſſe</l>
               <l>The path that would haue led vs on to ioy,</l>
               <l>And made vs tread the maze of all annoy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To ſowre our ſweet, lo what miſhap befell,</l>
               <l>An inſurrection in Northamptonſhire:</l>
               <l>Robin of Redſdale, curſed impe of hell,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:8"/>Who like ſome furie, with his hel-bred fire,</l>
               <l>Enrag'd the madnes of the rebels ſo,</l>
               <l>They like diſtracted men to Grafton go.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where by the force of boiſterous curſed hand,</l>
               <l>My father, then Earle Riuers, they did take:</l>
               <l>My brother, Sir Iohn Woodvile, did withſtand</l>
               <l>The rebels force, but oh he was too weake.</l>
               <l>Farre ouermatch'd was ſonne and fathers force,</l>
               <l>For without law, or iuſtice, or remorſe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They in Northampton, each did loſe his head:</l>
               <l>Nor Iudge, nor Iurie, had them ouerthrowne:</l>
               <l>With cruell rigor was their ſentence read,</l>
               <l>It nothing booted them to make their mone.</l>
               <l>Thus an oblation to that furious faction,</l>
               <l>Their blouds were made, ô moſt deteſted action!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Malicious Warwicke, in a ſhew of loue,</l>
               <l>Wrapt his diſpleaſure at his Soueraignes match:</l>
               <l>And gained leaue, for health freſh aire to proue,</l>
               <l>When Serpent-like he time and meanes did watch,</l>
               <l>To plucke King Edward from his throne inueſted,</l>
               <l>That ſo the ſeeds of ciuill warre deteſted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſubtilly with faire alluring words,</l>
               <l>Did draw the hearts of all he could perſwade:</l>
               <l>Not to obey, but to reſiſt with ſwords,</l>
               <l>Their lawfull King, againſt the oath they made.</l>
               <l>And ſo miſled the people, to attempt</l>
               <l>That which with loſſe of liues they did repent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:8"/>
               <l>See here the fickle minds the common ſort</l>
               <l>Of people beare, that not reſpecting right,</l>
               <l>Nor iuſt ſucceſſion, onely by report,</l>
               <l>And light beliefe of others, bend their might,</l>
               <l>Hazard their liues and lands, pollute their fame,</l>
               <l>With ſhamefull blot of traitors hatefull name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I grant my ſtate was meane, yet not ſo baſe,</l>
               <l>Iuſtly to be reputed odious:</l>
               <l>Nor did I ſpring from ſuch a ſeruile race,</l>
               <l>As might moue VVarwicke to be trecherous</l>
               <l>Vnto his King: for oft it hath bene ſeene,</l>
               <l>As meane a Lady hath bene made a Queene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But when vile rancor boyld in Warwicks breſt,</l>
               <l>He gladly tooke the ſimpleſt ſhew of cauſe,</l>
               <l>To leuie armes; and neuer would giue reſt</l>
               <l>Vnto his thoughts, vntill againſt all lawes</l>
               <l>He raiſd an armie gainſt King Edwards force,</l>
               <l>And by ill fortune gaue the King the worſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For in the night he ſodainly ſurpriſde</l>
               <l>King Edwards tent neare Wolney, where the King</l>
               <l>Litle ſuſpecting what his foe deuiſde,</l>
               <l>Securely ſlept, but then oh piteous thing,</l>
               <l>Hearing a noiſe he cald vnto his guard,</l>
               <l>But they were ſlaine, and he was clapt in ward.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And thence from Warwicke, in the night conueyed</l>
               <l>To Midlam Caſtle, where he did remaine:</l>
               <l>There in the Biſhops charge a while he ſtayed,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:9"/>Vntill he did for want of aire complaine:</l>
               <l>And by that meanes had leaue for pleaſure ſake,</l>
               <l>To hawke or hunt, the change of aire to take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which being once obtaind, King Edward thought</l>
               <l>It was the high way to his libertie:</l>
               <l>Plotting how this and that might beſt be wrought,</l>
               <l>And not procure his keepers iealouſie,</l>
               <l>Ought to miſtruſt; tis hard for to deuiſe</l>
               <l>A ſecret ſlight, to circumuent the wiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whether the Biſhop of himſelfe did giue</l>
               <l>So large a ſcope vnto the captiue King:</l>
               <l>Or Warwicks conſcience inwardly did grieue,</l>
               <l>That he had done ſo trecherous a thing:</l>
               <l>And therefore will'd the Biſhop let him haue,</l>
               <l>What libertie ſoeuer he did craue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ile not diſpute how it did come to paſſe,</l>
               <l>Though many thinke, that Warwicke did conſent</l>
               <l>To ſet him free: but be it as it was,</l>
               <l>All doubts to cleare, the King did ſoone preuent</l>
               <l>The fury of his foes, with heedfull care,</l>
               <l>To tread the path that might eſcape the ſnare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And by good fortune it did happen ſo,</l>
               <l>Sir William Stanley with a troupe of men,</l>
               <l>Met with the King as he to hunt did go:</l>
               <l>It was in vaine to argue where or when</l>
               <l>He ſhould be redeliuered, for decree</l>
               <l>Had cleare reſolu'd, to ſet King Edward free.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:9"/>
               <l>And thoſe that had the charge of his returne,</l>
               <l>Vnto whoſe care the Biſhop did commit</l>
               <l>The guarding of the King, were loth to ſpurne</l>
               <l>Againſt the pricke, accounting it no wit</l>
               <l>To offer force, where ſuch attempts were vaine,</l>
               <l>Which raſh reſiſtance might procure their paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Determinately therefore they agreed,</l>
               <l>With ſwifteſt ſpeed vnto their Lord to tell:</l>
               <l>How euilly their ſport that day did ſpeed,</l>
               <l>Which newes they knew would nothing pleaſe him well:</l>
               <l>But well or ill, there was no remedie,</l>
               <l>The King was gone paſt their recouerie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To Lancaſter, where then Lord Haſtings lay,</l>
               <l>The King made thither with all ſpeed he might:</l>
               <l>From thence, aſſur'd of friends, he tooke his way</l>
               <l>To London, whence (although his cauſe was right)</l>
               <l>He was enforc'd to Lin to ſhape his courſe,</l>
               <l>Of raging ſeas t'abide good hap or worſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To Burgondie with wind and ſaile he plide,</l>
               <l>There to recouer forces, helpe and aide,</l>
               <l>Of that great Duke: now marke what did betide,</l>
               <l>The boiſterous waues and aduerſe winds delayd</l>
               <l>His direct courſe; the Eaſterlings at ſea,</l>
               <l>Thought to haue made K. Edwards ſhip their prey.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His ſhip being ſmall, with helpe of ſaile did beare</l>
               <l>Such forewind ſpeed, that in deſpite of foe,</l>
               <l>It ranne ſo neare the ſhore, at Alquemare</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:10"/>Their ſhips drew deeper, that they could not go</l>
               <l>So neare the towne, but were compeld to ride</l>
               <l>At ancor there, attending the next tide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In the meane time Lord Gronture gouernor,</l>
               <l>In humbleſt maner welcomed the King,</l>
               <l>And charg'd the Eaſterlings to touch no ſhore,</l>
               <l>Commanding them not to attempt the thing,</l>
               <l>That to the Engliſh might offenſiue be:</l>
               <l>Thus was the King from dangerous foes ſet free.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But when the rumor through the land was blowne,</l>
               <l>That Edward was inforc'd to flie the land:</l>
               <l>And that the certaintie thereof was knowne,</l>
               <l>O in what deſperate ſtate did all they ſtand</l>
               <l>That were his friends! but vnto me his wife,</l>
               <l>No hope was left of ſafetie, friends, or life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now to the hardeſt cenſure I appeale,</l>
               <l>What world of woes oppreſt my ſoule with griefe:</l>
               <l>How could I hide my ſorrowes, or conceale</l>
               <l>My horror? for no hope of my reliefe,</l>
               <l>On any ſide, I no way could deſcrie,</l>
               <l>But gloomy death, and endleſſe miſerie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which ſad proſpect did threaten hard euent,</l>
               <l>To wretched me, of all good hap forſaken:</l>
               <l>Deſpaire attended me; no way I went,</l>
               <l>But by ſad thoughts my thoughts were ouertaken.</l>
               <l>Pale death my maſter was, and at my helme</l>
               <l>Stood terror, all my ioyes to ouerwhelme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:10"/>
               <l>In this red ſea which was not nauigable,</l>
               <l>My weather-beaten barke was runne aground:</l>
               <l>I thought to find ſome place auaileable,</l>
               <l>Where I might ſtrike my ſaile, and not be drownd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>The ſanctuary a moſt ſacred place,</l>
               <l>I fled vnto, hoping to find ſome grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such grace I meane, as to a wretched ſoule</l>
               <l>Yeelds comfort in extremes, neare drownd in griefe:</l>
               <l>There willingly my ſelfe I did inrole</l>
               <l>'Mongſt miſerable ſoules voide of reliefe:</l>
               <l>But that the reuerence of that holy place,</l>
               <l>Was a protection to them in that caſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And in that place I had not long remaind,</l>
               <l>But to the world Edward the fift I brought:</l>
               <l>Where like a poore mans child I not diſdaind</l>
               <l>To haue him Chriſtned, though ſo meane a thought</l>
               <l>Did nothing fit the mind of any Queene,</l>
               <l>(Who chuſeth leaſt of ils we wiſe eſteeme.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The pooreſt man, whoſe labour gets his pay,</l>
               <l>Whoſe court a cottage is, doth at ſuch time,</l>
               <l>More coſt beſtow on ſuch a ſolemne day,</l>
               <l>Then I had meanes to giue that child of mine:</l>
               <l>The Goſſips and chiefe credit of the troope,</l>
               <l>Were th'Abbot, Prior, and the Lady Scroope.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where was my cloth of ſtate, my canopie,</l>
               <l>Ladies of honor to attend my will?</l>
               <l>Where my rich hangings of rare tapeſtrie,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:11"/>The ſtatelieſt banquets, that deuice or skill</l>
               <l>Could ſet before vs? where the ſongs of mirth,</l>
               <l>To tell the world, we ioyd a Princes birth?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My ſtate and grace, of all the world neglected,</l>
               <l>Onely a naked name of Queene then left me:</l>
               <l>My neareſt friends arreſted or ſuſpected,</l>
               <l>With traitors blot, from which they were as free</l>
               <l>As new borne babes, yet were they ouerthrowne;</l>
               <l>Was euer ſuch a cruell tyrant knowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The troope of gallants, that once fawn'd on me,</l>
               <l>My fortune-followers, now they all are gone:</l>
               <l>My pompe and complements for my degree,</l>
               <l>Are vaniſht cleane, and I am caſt vpon</l>
               <l>The rocke, whereon alas I was vndone,</l>
               <l>Before my prime of pleaſure was begun.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O all was gone, and I my ſelfe deiected</l>
               <l>From Court and Crowne to fatall miſerie:</l>
               <l>Of Lord nor Lady graced nor reſpected,</l>
               <l>But headlong throwne into aduerſitie.</l>
               <l>Oh let no creature liue ſecure of ſtate,</l>
               <l>For Kings themſelues are ſubiects vnto fate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let meane mens wiues imagine what it is</l>
               <l>To want things fitting them in ſuch a caſe:</l>
               <l>I of all princely ornaments did miſſe,</l>
               <l>Was glad of ſuch as ſeruile were and baſe:</l>
               <l>Thus fortunes wheele, ſome vp, ſome downe doth toſſe,</l>
               <l>And I enforc'd perforce did beare this croſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:11"/>
               <l>O that I had a world of willing eares,</l>
               <l>That patiently would heare my ſorrowes told:</l>
               <l>And in this ſad diſcourſe to lend me teares,</l>
               <l>When they the map of my miſhaps behold:</l>
               <l>But ô the world ſhrowds in obliuion,</l>
               <l>Their name and fame, that to the earth are gone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My King was fled, my friends themſelues did ſhrowd</l>
               <l>Vnder the couert of my enemies:</l>
               <l>The new made gouerner, inſolent and proud;</l>
               <l>Hatefull to me, and all my progenie:</l>
               <l>Ten thouſand deaths, yea trebled miſchiefe fall</l>
               <l>Vpon his head, that ſowrd my ſweet with gall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay more then ſo, that wrongd not onely me,</l>
               <l>But to their King were inſtruments of ill:</l>
               <l>Curſed and odious let ſuch traitors be,</l>
               <l>That howſoeuer to effect their will,</l>
               <l>Regardleſſe of all wrong, againſt all right,</l>
               <l>Dares to take armes againſt their King to fight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So long, too long, with ſmall or no regard,</l>
               <l>I in that ſanctuary did remaine,</l>
               <l>Vntill at length for certaine truth I heard,</l>
               <l>That princely Edward, with a martiall traine,</l>
               <l>At Rauenſprugh neare Humber head was landed,</l>
               <l>With many a gallant warlikly attended.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which how it ioyd my ſoule, no tongue can tell:</l>
               <l>Then vnto God I did deuoutly pray,</l>
               <l>To caſt all Edwards foes as low as hell,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:12"/>And giue to him a ſafe victorious day,</l>
               <l>That he in triumph, with hearts ioy might ſee</l>
               <l>His litle ſonne preſented him by me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whether my prayers were effectuall,</l>
               <l>Or Edwards valor, which the world renown'd:</l>
               <l>But all his foes got ſuch a heauie fall,</l>
               <l>That he with victory againe was crown'd,</l>
               <l>And many ſlaine; the reſt that reattempted</l>
               <l>Rebellious factions, they ſuch faults repented.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Warwicke and others of that traiterous faction,</l>
               <l>Being ſlaine and ouerthrowne, a iuſt reward</l>
               <l>For them that dealt in ſuch rebellious action;</l>
               <l>Their peacocks plumes were pluckt, their brauerie mard:</l>
               <l>Victorious Edward by the helpe of heauen,</l>
               <l>Reign'd after this, of yeares iuſt eleuen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But then, ô then, for ſeldome good things laſt,</l>
               <l>Fates enuious of earthly creatures good,</l>
               <l>With ſwifteſt ſpeed, and with a heedleſſe haſte,</l>
               <l>Cruell in action, glut themſelues in bloud</l>
               <l>Of any one that cometh next to hand:</l>
               <l>All men perforce within their furie ſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But Atropos the cruelſt of the three,</l>
               <l>That ſpins and winds, and cuts our threed of life,</l>
               <l>As one inchanted, ſeeing did not ſee,</l>
               <l>When ſhe did cut the threed that bred ſuch ſtrife:</l>
               <l>For by his too ſoone death my woes began,</l>
               <l>And tragicke fall of many a mightie man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:12"/>
               <l>My forepaſt ſorrowes might be termed ioyes,</l>
               <l>And all my griefes were ioyes compard to this:</l>
               <l>King Edward dide, with him dide all my ioyes,</l>
               <l>And I was baniſht from all earthly bliſſe,</l>
               <l>To the ſad tortures of an earthly hell,</l>
               <l>The leaſt of all my woes no tongue can tell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Seuen royall children to this King I bare,</l>
               <l>Edward the fift, by treaſon murthered;</l>
               <l>Richard his brother had a deadly ſhare,</l>
               <l>For they were both together ſmothered:</l>
               <l>Fiue daughters by this King I alſo had,</l>
               <l>Woſe fortunes, ſome were good and others bad.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When palefac'd death had ſeiz'd vpon my King,</l>
               <l>My Lord, my loue, the hope of all my ioy;</l>
               <l>And by that ſtroake had blemiſht euery thing,</l>
               <l>That might preſerue and keepe me from annoy:</l>
               <l>The Nobles droopt, the common people mournd,</l>
               <l>And all my hopes to ſad deſpaire were turnd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some ſparke of future good I hop'd to ſee,</l>
               <l>Since to the Crowne my ſonne by due deſcent</l>
               <l>Was heire apparent: but what ſtate ſo free,</l>
               <l>But truſt in treaſon brings to hard euent?</l>
               <l>Vſurping Richard ſuch a plot laid downe,</l>
               <l>To work their deaths; and gain himſelf the Crown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such fearfull thoughts my ſenſes ſo did fright,</l>
               <l>That ſome miſhap I feared would befall</l>
               <l>To the yong King: ſad viſions in the night</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:13"/>So troubled me, I could not ſleepe at all:</l>
               <l>Deuouring beaſts, but moſt of all the Boare,</l>
               <l>My tender child, me thought, with tusks did goare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From Ludlow towards London the yong King</l>
               <l>Did go to haue his right, the royall Crowne:</l>
               <l>Litle ſuſpecting trechery would ſpring,</l>
               <l>Nor that his vnkle Gloc'ſter would put downe</l>
               <l>The lawfull King, the ſonne of his owne brother;</l>
               <l>But tyrannie regards ne one ne other.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To heape more ſorrowes on my wounded heart,</l>
               <l>My brother the Lord Riuers was arreſted:</l>
               <l>Sir Richard Gray and Vaughan bare a part,</l>
               <l>As guiltie of the fact, which they deteſted:</l>
               <l>Whilſt in Northampton in their Inne they ſtayed,</l>
               <l>Vnwares alas they guiltleſſe were betrayed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The keyes of all the doores were ſafely kept</l>
               <l>By thoſe that ſought to worke their ouerthrow;</l>
               <l>Whilſt they nothing miſdoubting, ſoundly ſlept,</l>
               <l>Litle ſuſpecting vndeſerued woe</l>
               <l>Would light on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that to their Prince were loyal;</l>
               <l>But truth by treaſon tript, nere comes to triall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Gloc'ſter and Buckingham hauing effected</l>
               <l>Their bloudy plots gainſt ſuch as were my friends;</l>
               <l>A warrant was with ſpeed by them directed,</l>
               <l>To bring thoſe priſoners to vntimely ends:</l>
               <l>And from Northampton vnto Ponfret, they</l>
               <l>Like lambes to ſlaughter led, were ſent away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:13"/>
               <l>Sir Richard Ratcliffe hauing the commiſſion</l>
               <l>To him directed, that by ſuch a day</l>
               <l>He ſhould be carefull, with all expedition,</l>
               <l>Thoſe innocents moſt bloudily to ſlay:</l>
               <l>He acted it without due courſe of lawes,</l>
               <l>Or asking why, or what ſhould be the cauſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The cruell Dukes then poaſted with all ſpeed</l>
               <l>To Stony ſtratford, where the King then lay:</l>
               <l>The King, alas, not knowing of this deed,</l>
               <l>Said, Where's my vnkle? what doth cauſe him ſtay?</l>
               <l>Gloc'ſter replide, my kinred traitors were,</l>
               <l>As by due proofe his Maieſtie ſhould heare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Saying, they had conſpir'd to rule the State,</l>
               <l>To ouerthrow the Nobles of the land,</l>
               <l>To rule the King, and giue him the checke mate;</l>
               <l>All the Nobilitie in great feare did ſtand</l>
               <l>Of them that had of late bene too much grac'd,</l>
               <l>And now high time they ſhould be all diſplac'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And that the Lord Gray, brother to the King,</l>
               <l>And with the King in preſence at that time,</l>
               <l>Might well be charged with the ſelfe ſame thing;</l>
               <l>Thus did they plot the fall of me and mine.</l>
               <l>The King replide, that iuſtly he might ſweare,</l>
               <l>His brother Gray was innocent and cleare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And with thoſe words, teares trickled from his eies;</l>
               <l>But though that ſight was pitifull to ſee,</l>
               <l>It nought reclaimd them from their cruelties.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:14"/>What ſadder ſigne of griefe could euer be,</l>
               <l>Then that a King, whoſe word ſhould be a law,</l>
               <l>With teares ſhould plead, as though he ſtood in aw?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My father and my brethren murthered,</l>
               <l>In this might well be ſeene the future hap,</l>
               <l>Of ill preſaged fortune furthered,</l>
               <l>By thoſe two bloudie Dukes, that ſought to wrap</l>
               <l>In ſad deſpaire and death, me and my friends,</l>
               <l>And bring vs quickly to vntimely ends.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When I had heard of this vnlookt for lot,</l>
               <l>This vndeſerued crueltie inflicted</l>
               <l>Vpon my brother, who without all ſpot</l>
               <l>Had cleare remaind, and could not be conuicted</l>
               <l>Of any one conceiued thought of ill</l>
               <l>Againſt his King, in heart, in mind or will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnto the Sanctuary then I fled,</l>
               <l>My friends and children I did take with me:</l>
               <l>To ſcape their hands that ſought our blouds to ſhed,</l>
               <l>Cleare out of hope that euer I ſhould ſee</l>
               <l>My ſon receiue the Crowne; my feare prou'd true,</l>
               <l>Which ſhortly after I had cauſe to rue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The litle King was brought vnto the Tower,</l>
               <l>As ſureſt place of ſafetie for his perſon:</l>
               <l>Accurſed be that day and fatall hower,</l>
               <l>That ere he entred there: for his ſubuerſion</l>
               <l>Was by the Dukes in cruell faſhion wrought,</l>
               <l>When leaſt of death, alas, he had a thought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:14"/>
               <l>And to cut off Edwards poſteritie</l>
               <l>From ſitting in their Fathers regall ſeate,</l>
               <l>My yonger ſonne with me in Sanctuarie,</l>
               <l>They plotted how they might by falſe deceit</l>
               <l>Take him from me; that to augment my paine,</l>
               <l>Euen at one inſtant they might both be ſlaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which to effect, the Cardinall was ſent</l>
               <l>To deale with me, to get my ſecond ſonne</l>
               <l>Into their hands, which deed I now repent:</l>
               <l>I thought full litle that they would haue done,</l>
               <l>In action or in thought the ſmalleſt thing,</l>
               <l>That any way might preiudice their King.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Cardinall alledg'd the Kings deſire</l>
               <l>To haue his brother in his companie:</l>
               <l>And that it kindled had the Nobles ire,</l>
               <l>That I ſhould doubt, or be in iealouſie</l>
               <l>Of them that were the rulers of the land,</l>
               <l>And were allide to them in natures band.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I not denide, but that I thought it fit,</l>
               <l>For brethren then in their minoritie</l>
               <l>To be together, if that were onely it,</l>
               <l>That cauſed them of the nobilitie</l>
               <l>To wiſh to haue my ſonne ſent to his brother,</l>
               <l>That they might ſport and play one with another.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My trembling heart did inwardly ſo quake,</l>
               <l>That I did feare, as then I knew not what:</l>
               <l>My inward thoughts enforc'd my ioynts to ſhake,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:15"/>As fearing this, and then miſdoubting that:</l>
               <l>But what to feare, alas I could not tell,</l>
               <l>But that my ſonne was ſickly, and not well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I told the Card'nall, that not long before,</l>
               <l>A dangerous ſickneſſe had afflicted him,</l>
               <l>And that cold aire would aggrauate it more;</l>
               <l>And therefore I being neareſt of his kin,</l>
               <l>Was fitteſt yet to keepe him there with me,</l>
               <l>For then his mother who could dearer be?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And to the Card'nall I with teares did ſay,</l>
               <l>Recall to mind my Lord, the grace and loue,</l>
               <l>The King my husband gaue you many yeares,</l>
               <l>As by experience you did daily proue:</l>
               <l>Requite that loue to his poſteritie,</l>
               <l>When moſt you thinke them in extremitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as I here deliuer vnto you</l>
               <l>This litle Duke, the brother to your King:</l>
               <l>If you to him hereafter proue vntrue,</l>
               <l>Reſt moſt aſſur'd that ſuch a hainous thing</l>
               <l>Shall euer be a blemiſh to your fame,</l>
               <l>And vtterly extinguiſh your good name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And though perhaps you thinke my words are vaine,</l>
               <l>And that I vndertake a needleſſe taske,</l>
               <l>To giue aduice, where I ſhould entertaine</l>
               <l>Your ſacred counſell: and of you ſhould aske,</l>
               <l>What I ſhould do in ſuch a caſe as this,</l>
               <l>Whereon depends the hope of all my bliſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:15"/>
               <l>The ſacred reuerence, and the great eſteeme</l>
               <l>I beare to you, forbids me to miſtruſt</l>
               <l>Your loyaltie, and yet you muſt not deeme</l>
               <l>My feare is cauſleſſe, my miſdoubts vniuſt:</l>
               <l>For many men to gaine themſelues a Crowne,</l>
               <l>Haue bene regardleſſe whom they did caſt downe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But you vpon your ſoule do here proteſt,</l>
               <l>You will defend, to th'vtmoſt of your power,</l>
               <l>My ſonnes, if any ſeeme them to moleſt.</l>
               <l>Their yeares are yong, yet ſpringing is their flower;</l>
               <l>Long may they liue, increaſe of ioyes to ſee:</l>
               <l>It fits them die that old and withered be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I know you may, and doubt not but you will</l>
               <l>Be a ſtrong ſtay to the vnſure eſtate</l>
               <l>Of both my ſonnes: if any ſeeke to ſpill</l>
               <l>Their blouds, you may in time preuent the hate,</l>
               <l>And crueltie of ſuch, if you haue care,</l>
               <l>With watchfull eye for to diſcerne the ſnare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Since on your truſt I do my hopes repoſe,</l>
               <l>And all my future good doth now rely</l>
               <l>On the performance of your vowes and oathes,</l>
               <l>Feare ſtill the worſt, leſt all too ſuddenly</l>
               <l>Their deaths be wrought; ô let no foule corruption</l>
               <l>Make you conſent to innocents deſtruction.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet ſince the King and Councell did require,</l>
               <l>And ſent for him, I would not ſay them nay,</l>
               <l>But gaue conſent to that they did deſire:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:16"/>And to the Cardinall, without longer ſtay,</l>
               <l>My litle ſonne I gaue, and with a kiſſe</l>
               <l>Tooke leaue of him, and of all earthly bliſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whole ſeas of teares did ouerflow my face,</l>
               <l>Griefe ſtopt my tongue, I could not ſpeake at all:</l>
               <l>The little child diſtild ſalt teares apace,</l>
               <l>And on his mothers name he oft did call:</l>
               <l>I was chiefe mourner, he to beare a part,</l>
               <l>Sent ſighs and teares from his lamenting heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Richard the third.</note>When thus the Boare had ſeiz'd into his hand,</l>
               <l>Them whom he thought were obiects in his way,</l>
               <l>He did not long in doubtfull cenſure ſtand,</l>
               <l>But fell to action without all delay,</l>
               <l>Foreknowing well that he that acts an euill,</l>
               <l>Muſt neither thinke on God, nor feare the deuill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And hauing found a meanes and inſtrument,</l>
               <l>That dared ſpeake vntruths in any thing:</l>
               <l>One Doctor Shaw, with ſcandalous intent,</l>
               <l>Preach'd at Pauls croſſe, that my deceaſſed King</l>
               <l>A baſtard was, vnlawfully begotten:</l>
               <l>What hel-hound would ſuch infamie haue ſpoken?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And that the Duke then being but Protector,</l>
               <l>He was the perfect picture of his father;</l>
               <l>And therefore he was true and right ſucceſſor</l>
               <l>Vnto the Crowne: the hearers ſtraight did gather</l>
               <l>The falſhood of the words that he did teach;</l>
               <l>And went their way, &amp; wold not heare him preach.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:16"/>
               <l>And with his tongue, the touchſtone of defame,</l>
               <l>He moſt vntruly there to them did ſay,</l>
               <l>My children baſtards were: thus voide of ſhame,</l>
               <l>He ſought to worke the ruine and decay</l>
               <l>Of me and mine: ô let his ſoule in hell,</l>
               <l>For euermore in endleſſe torments dwell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And more then that, if more then that may be,</l>
               <l>Let thoſe that liue of his poſteritie,</l>
               <l>Hatefull to all, of high or low degree,</l>
               <l>Leade odious liues in depth of miſerie,</l>
               <l>Where neither Sunne nor Moone may giue them light:</l>
               <l>Loe this ſhall be my prayer day and night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But whither wade I now? I muſt not rage,</l>
               <l>Though extreame griefe doth make my heart to vexe,</l>
               <l>And paſſe decorum for a penſiue ſtage,</l>
               <l>It's but the imperfection of my ſexe:</l>
               <l>A woman hath no meanes to right her wrong,</l>
               <l>But by the ſharpe and bitterneſſe of tongue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which if too much I ſeeme herein to vſe,</l>
               <l>Condemne me not, but paſſion that doth cauſe</l>
               <l>Me thus the bounds of mildneſſe to refuſe,</l>
               <l>And vſe my tongue, the weapon of our lawes,</l>
               <l>And ſcourge for them that wrongfully offend vs,</l>
               <l>And onely refuge left for to defend vs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When this was bruted by this ſlandering Doctor,</l>
               <l>And that with baſtardie my bloud was tainted:</l>
               <l>For he was fit to be the diuels Proctor,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:17"/>Or tell a tale of Belſabub new painted,</l>
               <l>By ſome magitian lately came from hell:</l>
               <l>Such fained things he ſpared not to tell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then did vſurping Richard claime the Crowne,</l>
               <l>And by the helpe of Buckingham he gaind</l>
               <l>The regall Seate, not caring who went downe,</l>
               <l>So he might hit the marke whereat he aimd:</l>
               <l>The Crowne by bloud and tyrannie he won,</l>
               <l>To friend or foe regardleſſe what was done.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet though King Richard did deſire to ſee</l>
               <l>The death of both my children, whom he thought</l>
               <l>Did dim his title to the Crowne; yet he</l>
               <l>Could not deuiſe by whom to haue it wrought:</l>
               <l>The fact ſo odious was, that neuer any</l>
               <l>Would vndertake it, though he proued many.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>New meanes to trie, a letter was directed</l>
               <l>To him that was Lieutenant of the Tower,</l>
               <l>One Brackenbury, that as he reſpected</l>
               <l>King Richards fauour, at the inſtant hower</l>
               <l>And ſight thereof, he then with ſpeed ſhould ſlay</l>
               <l>The two yong Princes, without all delay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sir Robert Brackenbury hauing read</l>
               <l>The letter, he did preſently reply,</l>
               <l>Their bloud ſhould neuer by his meanes be ſhed,</l>
               <l>Though for refuſing he were ſure to die.</l>
               <l>Which anſwer when the King did heare, he then</l>
               <l>Did deeply ſweare, there was no truſt in men.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:17"/>
               <l>I ſee, quoth he, this world is full of euill,</l>
               <l>Promotions ſoone forgotten, fauors vaine:</l>
               <l>I would ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſent my man vnto the deuill,</l>
               <l>But he will giue me leaue to take that paine</l>
               <l>My ſelfe: but yet I hope to find ſome friends,</l>
               <l>That will not faile to bring them to their ends.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And at the laſt he did find out a mate,</l>
               <l>No man, a monſter of ſome tygers kind,</l>
               <l>Hoping to raiſe by crueltie his ſtate;</l>
               <l>When he perceiu'd King Richards bloudy mind,</l>
               <l>Voide of all grace, poſſeſt with villanie,</l>
               <l>Offerd himſelfe to worke their tragedie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now prepare your eares to heare the ſound</l>
               <l>Of ſaddeſt woe, and extreame crueltie:</l>
               <l>Was euer ſuch a bloudy butcher found,</l>
               <l>That euer dared act ſuch tyrannie,</l>
               <l>As was this traitor, Terrill was his name,</l>
               <l>That gaue conſent to worke his Princes bane?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A ſtrict command, the King by Terrill ſent</l>
               <l>To Brackenbury, charging him thereby,</l>
               <l>That all the keyes he ſhould incontinent</l>
               <l>Deliuer vp to Terrill willingly,</l>
               <l>For that one night he did the King obay,</l>
               <l>Yeeld the keyes, and ſadly went his way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Night being come, that ſhrowdeth many a ſinne</l>
               <l>From eyes of men, but not from ſight of God:</l>
               <l>He knowes the thoughts before the deeds begin,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:18"/>And will reuenge and puniſh with his rod,</l>
               <l>Without reſpect of perſons, all alike:</l>
               <l>The mightieſt King he will in iuſtice ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ike.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Into the Tower by ſecret dores that night,</l>
               <l>Terrill with ſuch as were wrought to his will,</l>
               <l>Forreſt and Dighton entered by ſlight</l>
               <l>Into their chamber, reſolute to kill</l>
               <l>The ſleeping Princes, who being voide of feare,</l>
               <l>Did litle thinke their deaths had bene ſo neare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And when the Princes both within one bed</l>
               <l>Together ſlept, embracing one the other,</l>
               <l>Thoſe cruell villaines by the diuell led,</l>
               <l>The litle brethren in their beds did ſmother:</l>
               <l>Thus from the ſleepe that nature forc'd them to,</l>
               <l>They neuer wak'd to tell who wrought their wo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whether in water, or in ſacred ground,</l>
               <l>They caſt or laid the bodies murthered,</l>
               <l>It's yet vnknowne, the place was neuer found,</l>
               <l>But in their beds they thus were ſmothered:</l>
               <l>O neuer villaines acted ſuch a deed,</l>
               <l>The thought wherof doth make my ſoule to bleed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This murther done, this moſt deteſted fact,</l>
               <l>Being once performed by that damned crew,</l>
               <l>Vpon the litle Princes; Terrill packt,</l>
               <l>And like ſome fury to the Court he ſlew,</l>
               <l>The maner how, vnto the King to tell,</l>
               <l>And euery accident as it befell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:18"/>
               <l>They had no wounds, by which it might appeare</l>
               <l>That violently ſo their blouds were ſhed;</l>
               <l>But as by natures courſe they periſht were;</l>
               <l>And that their bodies being ſcarcely dead,</l>
               <l>Vnder a paire of ſtayres within the Tower,</l>
               <l>Were caſt a prey for Serpents to deuoure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The bloudy King was pleaſed with the deed,</l>
               <l>But did diſlike the baſeneſſe of the place,</l>
               <l>Where they had caſt the bodies; and with ſpeed,</l>
               <l>Terror of conſcience, or ſome ſparke of grace</l>
               <l>Did worke remorſe in him, and therefore he</l>
               <l>Gaue charge their bodies ſhould remoued be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But whither, where, or to what place aſſign'd,</l>
               <l>No hiſtory doth to this age relate:</l>
               <l>A Prieſt, ſome ſay, their bodies there did find,</l>
               <l>And mou'd with pitie, did commiſerate,</l>
               <l>Such royall babes, of life and Crowne bereft,</l>
               <l>Should in ſo vile a filthy place be left.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And did remoue them, where he thought more fit</l>
               <l>And ſacred place for princely obſequies:</l>
               <l>Which reu'rent deed deſerueth to be writ</l>
               <l>In golden letters, that poſterities</l>
               <l>May learne of him, that Chriſtians ought to haue</l>
               <l>A decent place to lay their dead in graue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then if a generall regard be had</l>
               <l>Of thoſe that die, although they be but ſuch,</l>
               <l>Whoſe births were baſe, whoſe liues were thought but bad:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:19"/>The honor due to Princes is ſo much,</l>
               <l>As gods on earth they honor'd ought to be</l>
               <l>Of all eſtates, of high or low degree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When I had heard of this extremeſt ill,</l>
               <l>Griefe ſtopt my ſpeech, ſorrowes oppreſt my heart:</l>
               <l>I was enforc'd, although againſt my will,</l>
               <l>From all delights and pleaſures to depart,</l>
               <l>Nothing was left but ſorrow, griefe and care,</l>
               <l>Thus all my hope was turnd to ſad deſpaire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let neuer heauens yeeld ſuch a chearfull ſmile,</l>
               <l>That may yeeld comfort to that damned ſoule,</l>
               <l>That did not feare to do a deed ſo vile;</l>
               <l>Let helliſh furies, all their names inrole</l>
               <l>In that blacke book, which to augment their paine,</l>
               <l>As record of their deeds doth ſtill remaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let vglieſt ſhape of moſt abhorred deuill,</l>
               <l>Fire-ſpitting fiends in that infernall lake,</l>
               <l>Dayly torment them that deuiſde this euill,</l>
               <l>Or gaue conſent, or the leaſt part did take,</l>
               <l>To murther him that was their lawfull King,</l>
               <l>And crop his flower, whilſt it was in the ſpring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To breake the branch that did but newly bud;</l>
               <l>Nay more then ſo, to plucke vp by the roote,</l>
               <l>The ſpringing plant next of the royall bloud:</l>
               <l>Though this to tell my griefe, is litle boote,</l>
               <l>And all in vaine I do my woes repleate,</l>
               <l>Becauſe in me all ſorrowes are compleate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:19"/>
               <l>Yet needs I muſt, nature enforceth me,</l>
               <l>I was their mother, they the royall ſeed</l>
               <l>Of my deare Lord, whom yet me thinkes I ſee</l>
               <l>Vrging reuenge for this moſt wicked deed;</l>
               <l>And ſhall not I with him ſtill beare a part,</l>
               <l>In prayer, in woe, in ioy, or griefe of heart?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O needs I muſt, and euer gladly will</l>
               <l>Follow his ghoſt, with ſeruiceable loue,</l>
               <l>And euermore be preſt and ready ſtill,</l>
               <l>With ſighes and teares t'importune mightie loue,</l>
               <l>To grant the prayers of my beloued King,</l>
               <l>For his deſires were iuſt in euery thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If more I ſpeake then well be cometh me;</l>
               <l>In curious eye and eare if I too farre</l>
               <l>Forget my ſelfe, let this my anſwer be,</l>
               <l>He was my glorious Sun, no twinkling ſtarre:</l>
               <l>They that on earth do beare the Scepter royall,</l>
               <l>To them their ſubiects hearts ought to be loyall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then if a ſubiect muſt adore his King;</l>
               <l>If he that is the King of Kings, command</l>
               <l>Faith, dutie, loue, of all in euery thing</l>
               <l>To be performd, if firme his act ſhall ſtand;</l>
               <l>Why then much more ſhould I that was his wife,</l>
               <l>Performe my dutie in and after life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For after life the ghoſt hath libertie,</l>
               <l>Of ioyes or griefe to beare a feeling part:</l>
               <l>And though ſome women through infirmitie,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:20"/>Their frailtie or their fickleneſſe of heart,</l>
               <l>When death once ſeizeth on their deareſt friend,</l>
               <l>Their former loues are quickly at an end:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet what of that, my thoughts were pitcht on hie,</l>
               <l>I lou'd no meaner perſon then a King;</l>
               <l>Then with his life why ſhould my fancies die?</l>
               <l>Why ſhould ſucceeding ages after ſing</l>
               <l>To my reproch, that I that was a Queene,</l>
               <l>In baſer choice to ſport was euer ſeene?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Richard the third, rightly cald th'vſurper,</l>
               <l>Requited thoſe that were his truſtie friends</l>
               <l>With ſodaine death; and his deuice to further,</l>
               <l>Plotted vntruths to bring them to their ends:</l>
               <l>Then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they thought their fortunes were at hieſt,</l>
               <l>Then was their woe their fall, and death the nieſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But good or bad, this tyrant being King,</l>
               <l>Who ſo he hated, or did ſtand in doubt,</l>
               <l>Would not conſent to him in euery thing,</l>
               <l>To take their liues, all wayes he caſt about,</l>
               <l>By ſodaine action, or ſurmiſde pretence,</l>
               <l>Without their heads he ſent them packing thence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In this extreame, alas, what way was left</l>
               <l>For wretched me, but to deſpaire and die?</l>
               <l>Of hope and hap, of friends and all bereft,</l>
               <l>What ſhould I do, or whither ſhould I flie?</l>
               <l>But ſtill in danger of my mortall foe,</l>
               <l>To wiſh for death the end of earthly woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:20"/>
               <l>Two yeares he reign'd in feare and bloudie ſtrife,</l>
               <l>In which meane time in Sanctuarie I</l>
               <l>Did ſhroud my ſelfe, to ſaue my wretched life,</l>
               <l>And linger out my dayes in miſerie:</l>
               <l>Though death farre better was in ſuch a caſe,</l>
               <l>My womans heart could hardly death embrace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His breach of faith, his odious cruelties,</l>
               <l>Firſt cauſed Buckingham to leuie armes:</l>
               <l>And in the North it cauſed mutinies,</l>
               <l>Men ſought to 'venge the many grieuous harmes,</l>
               <l>That wrongfully they ſaw him dayly do</l>
               <l>To all eſtates, as well to friend as foe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This made Earle Richmond find ſo many friends,</l>
               <l>When he layd claime vnto the Engliſh Crowne:</l>
               <l>Who doth not wiſh all tyrants ſpeedie ends?</l>
               <l>Who will not helpe to caſt a tyrant downe?</l>
               <l>The King of Kings that all mens acts doth ſee,</l>
               <l>Will neuer let ſuch men vnpuniſht be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not long before Earle Richmond came to ſhore,</l>
               <l>King Richard ſent to me, perſwading men</l>
               <l>To make excuſe for what was done before,</l>
               <l>With promiſes of gracious proffers then:</l>
               <l>They layd long ſiege vnto my weake defence,</l>
               <l>With vowes and oaths to cleare him from offence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With kindeſt promiſes of future good,</l>
               <l>To me or any one that I could name:</l>
               <l>I well conſidering in what caſe I ſtood,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:21"/>Grew milder, and at laſt did ſeeme to frame</l>
               <l>My ſelfe as pliant to their maſters will,</l>
               <l>Yet was my heart free from one thought of ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Eagle towring in the loftie skie,</l>
               <l>If he vnto his prey do kindneſſe vſe,</l>
               <l>Vnder whoſe ſtroake their life or death doth lie:</l>
               <l>Were it not madneſſe in them to refuſe</l>
               <l>His profferd fauour, ſince they muſt obay</l>
               <l>His will, becauſe they cannot ſcape away?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such was my caſe, although not ſo conſidered:</l>
               <l>He was the Eagle that was mounted hie,</l>
               <l>I and my friends the prey diſcomforted,</l>
               <l>Stood at his will to liue or elſe to die;</l>
               <l>Our ſafeties he did proffer, gold and loue,</l>
               <l>I was content our better haps to proue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He did deſire, but that I would conceiue</l>
               <l>A good opinion of his deeds to come,</l>
               <l>And not my ſelfe ſo fondly to deceiue,</l>
               <l>Miſtaking things that then were paſt and done:</l>
               <l>Alas, I knew it was then in his power,</l>
               <l>To date our liues one day, or but an hower.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My ſecret foes, if any ſuch there were,</l>
               <l>They knew, or at the leaſt they might haue knowne,</l>
               <l>I wiſht Earle Richmond well, and ioyd to heare</l>
               <l>That Richards ſtate ſhould ſoone be ouerthrowne:</l>
               <l>I did procure my friends, with power and will,</l>
               <l>To aide the Earle, King Richards bloud to ſpill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:21"/>
               <l>Which though in ſecret to my friends I ſaid,</l>
               <l>I durſt not but ſeeme pleaſed to forgiue</l>
               <l>All former faults, although in heart I praid,</l>
               <l>That cruell Richard might no longer liue</l>
               <l>To bathe in bloud: full oft on bended knee,</l>
               <l>With teares I praid, that I his death might ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What ſhould I hold you in a long diſcourſe?</l>
               <l>Faire words preuaild, and I did giue conſent;</l>
               <l>Knowing our fortunes hardly could be worſe,</l>
               <l>I with my daughters to his pallace went:</l>
               <l>Where he did giue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand, and ſtraightly charge,</l>
               <l>Our welcome ſhould be great, our freedome large.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I knew the time was neare, and then at hand,</l>
               <l>That Henry Earle of Richmond meant to trie,</l>
               <l>In warlike battell, with a valiant band,</l>
               <l>Either to winne the Crowne, or elſe to die:</l>
               <l>I knew what Noble men would take his part,</l>
               <l>I gaind him friends, and gaue to his my heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I ioyd to heare that Richard loſt the field;</l>
               <l>Who did not pray to ſee his ouerthrow?</l>
               <l>He being ſlaine, who did not freely yeeld?</l>
               <l>Each man was glad, and wiſht it might be ſo:</l>
               <l>Of Yorke and Lancaſter then grew the vnion,</l>
               <l>Whoſe former ſtrife wrought many mens co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The conquering King, according to his oath,</l>
               <l>Was married to my daughter preſently:</l>
               <l>Which to helpe forward no man ſeemed loth,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:22"/>But all were aiders, as fidelitie</l>
               <l>Did bind them to performe: this being done,</l>
               <l>I ioyd once more to haue a King my ſonne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Foole that I was, to glorie in the thing</l>
               <l>Which prou'd to me vnpleaſant in the end:</l>
               <l>I like the ſwan, before my death did ſing,</l>
               <l>As litle knowing what they did intend,</l>
               <l>That ſecretly conſpir'd to worke my fall,</l>
               <l>And ſodainly did turne my ſweete to gall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Henry the <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note>The ſecond yeare of this King Henries raigne,</l>
               <l>The Councell did decree, that wretched I,</l>
               <l>The more to aggrauate my griefe and paine,</l>
               <l>Should loſe my lands, and liue in penurie,</l>
               <l>Becauſe I did accept in outward ſhow,</l>
               <l>Of Richards kindneſſe. They did litle know,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How eaſily a captiuated man,</l>
               <l>Will yeeld to him that is his conqueror,</l>
               <l>And gladly pleaſe in any thing he can,</l>
               <l>The fury of a ſauage tormenter,</l>
               <l>Eſpecially in ſuch a caſe as this,</l>
               <l>Where wil might hurt, but could not help my wiſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I had too lately knowne his bloudy mind,</l>
               <l>I was vnable to withſtand his force:</l>
               <l>I knew no place of ſafetie where to find,</l>
               <l>My ſtate was like to grow from bad to worſe:</l>
               <l>Which made me willingly accept the good</l>
               <l>That he did vow to me and to my blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:22"/>
               <l>Alas, what could a ſilly woman do?</l>
               <l>My female frailtie might haue colourd this:</l>
               <l>I feard to taſte the furie of my foe,</l>
               <l>Becauſe my ſtrength was all too weake for his:</l>
               <l>I timorouſly did feare the bloudie ſlaughters,</l>
               <l>That he might do to me and to my daughters.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What hurt or danger to Earle Richmonds plot,</l>
               <l>Could my diſſembled peace with Richard be?</l>
               <l>What face ſo faire, but that a fault or ſpot,</l>
               <l>A partiall Iudge will ſay, he there doth ſee?</l>
               <l>It's better die, and not to liue at all,</l>
               <l>Then be ſo weake, with euery blaſt to fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When I was grac'd with fauour of my King,</l>
               <l>Whilſt he did liue that did ſupport and ſtay</l>
               <l>Thoſe whom I pleaſde into his grace to bring,</l>
               <l>All then was iuſt that I would do or ſay:</l>
               <l>He being gone, and that I was declining,</l>
               <l>At my eſtate how many were repining?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Had I bene cruell, couetous or ſtrange,</l>
               <l>When poore diſtreſſed ſuters to me cride,</l>
               <l>From good conceit to bad, then might they change:</l>
               <l>Had I the needy naked ſoule denide</l>
               <l>Of any helpe, that then was in my power,</l>
               <l>Then had I liu'd too long, if but an hower.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But if my heart did pitie widowes teares,</l>
               <l>The fatherleſſe if I did helpe to right,</l>
               <l>And ſet the needie free from many feares,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:23"/>Wherewith they were oppreſt by men of might:</l>
               <l>To all eſtates ſince I was then a friend,</l>
               <l>Why ſhould their gratefulneſſe ſo quickly end?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And more then ſo, not onely to forget</l>
               <l>Good turnes once done, but to requite them ill,</l>
               <l>That well deſeru'd of all in each reſpect;</l>
               <l>So farre ſo blindly to be led by will,</l>
               <l>Or vile ingratitude, the filthieſt ſinne,</l>
               <l>That euer humane creatures liued in.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If this had hapned in a land vnknowne,</l>
               <l>Where I had neuer liued as a Queene:</l>
               <l>Had this bene done by any but my owne,</l>
               <l>My griefes ſhould leſſe in all reſpects haue beene:</l>
               <l>What made the mightie Caeſar wiſh to die?</l>
               <l>The griefe that Brutus was his enemie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I thought all ſtormes of miſery were paſt,</l>
               <l>My daughter being married to the King;</l>
               <l>I thought my pleaſures then would euer laſt,</l>
               <l>I neuer lookt for any change of thing:</l>
               <l>My innocencie would not let me feare,</l>
               <l>The grieuous cenſure that was then ſo neare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Bermondſey Abbey in Southwarke neare London</note>With wounded heart, the remnant of my dayes,</l>
               <l>In th'Abbey of Bermondſey in teares I ſpent:</l>
               <l>Still death I wiſht, and hated thoſe delayes,</l>
               <l>That fearfull frailtie did to me preſent:</l>
               <l>I cald for death, and weary was to liue,</l>
               <l>For well I knew life could no pleaſures giue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:23"/>
               <l>And when the end of all my griefes drew nie,</l>
               <l>And that my date of life was neare expired,</l>
               <l>With willing heart I was content to die:</l>
               <l>And Atropos I earneſtly deſired,</l>
               <l>To cut the threed that did prolong my life,</l>
               <l>Becauſe in me all ſorrowes were ſo rife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My corps being dead, to Windſor was conuaid,</l>
               <l>And there interred fitting my degree,</l>
               <l>Euen in that place where my deare Lord was laid,</l>
               <l>There at this day the tombe is yet to ſee:</l>
               <l>Vnto which place, now I my griefes haue told,</l>
               <l>I muſt returne and ſhroud my ſelfe in mold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then did this Queene returne vnto her reſt,</l>
               <l>And vaniſht, leauing to my memorie</l>
               <l>Here to relate what ſhe to me rehearſt:</l>
               <l>In which recitall, if infirmitie</l>
               <l>Cauſe me forget that which I ſhould haue ſpoken:</l>
               <l>Imagine that which I haue now forgotten.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If ſuch the world in former times hath beene,</l>
               <l>That higheſt ſtates moſt ſubiect were to fall:</l>
               <l>How true ſaid ſhe, that late was Englands Queene,</l>
               <l>When ſhe her ſelfe at that time was in thrall,</l>
               <l>Loe yonder milk-maid liues more merrily,<note place="margin">It was the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Queene Elizabeth, when ſhe was priſoner in the time of Queen Mary.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Then I, that am of noble progenie?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not to be great, is therefore to be ſure</l>
               <l>From fortunes wracke: for this we dayly ſee,</l>
               <l>The higheſt trees do ſharpeſt ſtormes endure;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4783:24"/>When thoſe that planted in the valley be,</l>
               <l>Do ſeldome feare, and neuer feele the frowne</l>
               <l>Of boiſterous ſtormes, that others doth caſt downe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A vertuous life ſuruiues, when cruell death</l>
               <l>Hath ſoule from earthly body ſeuered,</l>
               <l>And hath bereft vs of our vitall breath,</l>
               <l>Yet worthy deeds ſhould be remembered:</l>
               <l>Succeeding ages ſhould them deifie,</l>
               <l>Whoſe liues and deaths were full of pietie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But what auaileth it to haue bene great,</l>
               <l>Or what, to haue bene friendly vnto many?</l>
               <l>When they ſhall come to ſit in ſorrowes ſeate,</l>
               <l>Themſelues ſhall ſeldome be relieu'd by any:</l>
               <l>For miſery hath many lookers on,</l>
               <l>And ſome that pitie, but adiutors none.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Queene was by deſcent of noble blood,</l>
               <l>Of vertuous life: yet in obliuions graue,</l>
               <l>How long hath ſhe in darke obſcureneſſe ſtood?</l>
               <l>Shall good deſerts, ſuch cold requitall haue?</l>
               <l>Vngratefull minds, that were by dutie bound,</l>
               <l>Her name and fame vnto the world to ſound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Queenes Colledge, which of her did take the name,</l>
               <l>In Cambridge as a monument doth ſtand,</l>
               <l>A worthy deed, deſeruing endleſſe fame;</l>
               <l>VVhich to maintaine, ſhe gaue ſufficient land:</l>
               <l>And ſome which in that Colledge haue bene bred,</l>
               <l>Might wel haue raiſd her fame though ſhe be dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4783:24"/>
               <l>Thus haue you heard, although abruptly pend,</l>
               <l>The fortunes of this Queene, and of her friends:</l>
               <l>Princes as well as beggers do depend</l>
               <l>On the Almighties will: what ere he ſends,</l>
               <l>None can preuent, or alter his decree,</l>
               <l>So firme, ſo ſure his ſecret iudgements be.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
